<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Root SYSTEM "wdr25_from_styles.dtd" [
]>
<Story>
    <fig href_fmt="images/v-LBN0525-bnew-big_fmt.png" href="file://images/v-LBN0525-bnew-big.tif"></fig>
    <Story>
        <fig href_fmt="images/v-LBN0525-AB-BIG_fmt.png" href="file://images/v-LBN0525-AB-BIG.tif"></fig>
        <chapter-number>Synthesis </chapter-number>
        <chapter-title>At crisis point: Countering harmful information, defending humanity</chapter-title>
        <normal>Harmful information is a pressing and pervasive challenge across all sectors of
            society, and a critical issue for organizations operating in humanitarian crises. Its
            impact on people in need, communities, responders, institutions and public trust in
            humanitarian action is profound. </normal>
        <normal>This report uses the term &#8216;harmful information&#8217; to focus on its impact
            and the responses &#8211; rather than rigid classifications, which are often politically
            charged and context dependent. While there is no universally agreed definition, for the
            purposes of this report, harmful information refers to <bold>information that has the
            potential to cause, contribute to or result in harm to an individual or entity</bold>.
            The term focuses attention on the harm itself, rather than on classifying the type of
            information being spread, which is often difficult to discern and constantly evolving. </normal>
        <normal-expanded>Harmful information is often framed as an online phenomenon, but
            humanitarian crises have long been shaped by rumours, myths and propaganda spread
            through offline means &#8211; word of mouth, pamphlets, radio and television broadcasts,
            community meetings and other official or semi-official channels. These offline dynamics
            remain deeply influential, especially in contexts with limited digital access or low
            media literacy. Importantly, harmful information often moves fluidly between online and
            offline spaces, amplifying its reach and creating real-world consequences for
            individuals and communities. </normal-expanded>
        <normal-expanded>In 2005, information was recognized as a form of disaster response. The
            concern then was one of omission &#8211; what people did not know &#8211; rather than
            the deliberate spread of damaging falsehoods. Twenty years on, that has changed. In
            2026, this report frames harmful information as a de facto <bold>crisis</bold>: one that
            undermines access of populations to humanitarian aid, erodes trust, misleads
            communities, deepens vulnerabilities and destabilizes social cohesion. It is a crisis
            because it is chronic and evolving &#8211; escalating, mutating and persisting across
            time and contexts. Harmful information does not simply &#8216;strike&#8217; once; it
            spreads, multiplies and compounds harm in many forms. It directly undermines the
            humanitarian sector&#8217;s ability to fulfil its core role: to alleviate suffering and
            protect life and human dignity, especially for people in the most vulnerable situations,
            while promoting respect for international laws, and upholding humanitarian principles
            and standards. Because harmful information can obstruct access, distort needs, fuel
            mistrust and even incite violence, it is no longer a peripheral concern. Responding to
            it is not optional &#8211; it is integral to protecting people and upholding
            humanitarian purpose. </normal-expanded>
        <normal>Managing harmful information is no longer just a communication challenge; it is an
            operational and ethical imperative that demands a whole-of-society response,
            encompassing public policy, institutional policies, preparedness, education and social
            awareness. Meeting this challenge requires a shift in how the humanitarian sector
            prepares for, mitigates and actively counters harmful information. The sector is neither
            fully equipped to respond nor solely responsible, making collective response essential.
            Some 60 organizations provided written contributions to this report, underscoring how
            seriously its impacts are now regarded across the sector and beyond. Across
            consultations, all recognized the growing danger of harmful information and many voiced
            hopes that this report can help build understanding and drive action. </normal>
        <normal>Historically, humanitarian standards and policies have often emerged in response to
            operational failures, access constraints or new technologies. Today, the challenge is no
            longer about the availability or accessibility of information, but about its
            reliability. This calls for clear sector-wide standards and guidance on how humanitarian
            actors should prepare for and respond to harmful information that are integrated into
            preparedness, risk assessment, protection and accountability frameworks and always
            adapted to local realities. </normal>
        <normal>Today, as the humanitarian sector confronts a new wave of technological change
            &#8211; artificial intelligence (AI) &#8211; the stakes are rising once again. AI is
            accelerating the production and spread of information at unprecedented speed and scale,
            lowering the barriers to entry for malicious actors to manipulate content and influence
            opinion. Governance frameworks are struggling to keep pace. </normal>
        <normal>Understanding how both information and technology are evolving is now essential to
            shaping effective responses to harmful information in humanitarian contexts. The scale
            and speed of harmful information today far exceed anything previously experienced.
            Navigating this flood of misleading, instrumentalized and targeted content has become
            critical to maintaining trust, protecting people&#8217;s safety and ensuring
            humanitarian response reaches people in need. </normal>
        <normal>In this landscape of harmful information, the report places <bold>trust, proximity,
            community and resilience</bold> at the centre of its analysis. </normal>
        <normal-expanded>This is particularly relevant in humanitarian contexts and within the
            information ecosystem: resilience cannot rest only on the shoulders of the people
            already most affected. It must be supported by broader systems that reduce
            vulnerability, enable equitable access to information and uphold rights. This requires
            investments in public trust, inclusive governance, meaningful accountability mechanisms
            and fair access to digital infrastructure and literacy.<bold> </bold>Without these
            foundations, resilience efforts risk becoming superficial &#8211; placing undue burden
            on the people and communities already most at risk. </normal-expanded>
        <h1>Harmful information is not background noise </h1>
        <normal>Harmful information is not background noise; it actively shapes how people
            understand crises, who they trust and whether they can access humanitarian assistance
            and protection. It influences safety and security both directly and indirectly. The
            struggle over harmful information is as much about cables as it is about content &#8211;
            the infrastructures and narratives that shape access, trust and power. </normal>
        <normal>As the information ecosystem becomes increasingly complex, so too must the capacity
            to read it, respond to it and protect affected populations, individuals and
            organizations from its harms. Navigating this ecosystem is now a core part of what it
            means to act in humanitarian crises. It must inform how responses are designed and
            implemented, while also driving advocacy for broader systemic change. </normal>
        <normal>The responsibility cannot rest solely with humanitarian organizations. Addressing
            harmful information requires enhancing resilience, building trust and deepening
            community engagement. It also demands coordinated, multi-stakeholder action &#8211; by
            governments, technology companies, media, communities and civil society organizations. </normal>
        <normal>Confronting harmful information is not optional. It requires nothing less than
            systemic change.<regular-italic> </regular-italic>It is essential to protecting lives,
            upholding humanitarian principles and ensuring that humanity itself remains the
            strongest counterforce to manipulation, mistrust and division. </normal>
        <normal>The task now is to ensure that the necessary safeguards, engagement, proximity,
            trust and resilience are not left to chance or profit, but are deliberately harnessed to
            protect people and enable principled humanitarian action.<fig
                href_fmt="images/P-CMR381-AB_fmt.jpg" href="file://images/P-CMR381-AB.tif"></fig>
        </normal>
        <h1-recommendations>Asks, aims and recommendations </h1-recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Asks </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Confront harmful information as a systemic humanitarian crisis that
            undermines safety, dignity and access. Integrate universally recognized rights,
            preparedness, accountability and transparency into crisis response, and act with the
            same urgency as for other humanitarian threats. Strengthen collaboration for sector-wide
            monitoring through rumour tracking, social listening and sentiment analysis.</recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Aims </normal-2c>
        <recommendations><bold>Protect people:</bold> Prioritize reliable and accurate information
            in crisis preparedness, response and recovery to safeguard safety, dignity and access. </recommendations>
        <recommendations><bold>Detect early and adapt:</bold> Monitor narratives, perceptions and
            sentiment to enable coordinated, transparent and timely responses. </recommendations>
        <recommendations><bold>Safeguard humanitarian action:</bold> Shield staff, volunteers,
            affected populations and operations from harmful information, cyber threats and
            disruptions to critical infrastructure, while preserving trust and legitimacy. </recommendations>
        <h3>Recommendations </h3>
        <h4>For governments and policy-makers </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Integrate harmful information management into crisis preparedness and
            response frameworks. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Invest in early warning and verification systems to deliver timely,
            reliable, life-saving information.</bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Uphold cyber norms and protect humanitarian organizations and critical
            infrastructure from malicious ICT use. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Establish clear legal and policy frameworks that support and protect
            humanitarian action from interference and harmful information campaigns. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>For technology platforms </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Prioritize rapid moderation and fact-checking in humanitarian crises &#8211;
            before, during and after crises &#8211; with effective escalation channels for
            humanitarian organizations. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Ensure tools function in low-bandwidth, multilingual and
            resource-constrained contexts. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Integrate purposeful friction into digital platforms &#8211; such as
            accuracy prompts, warning labels, &#8216;read-before-you-repost&#8217; nudges, and
            slower sharing pathways for unverified content &#8211; particularly in the context of
            humanitarian crises, to limit the rapid spread of harmful information and encourage more
            deliberate, informed user engagement. Adapt algorithms to reduce amplification of
            harmful narratives targeting humanitarian organizations, principled humanitarian action
            and affected populations. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Report transparently on moderation actions, algorithmic adjustments and
            impacts in humanitarian contexts. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Co-design crisis-response protocols with humanitarian actors to ensure
            interventions are timely, context specific and aligned with internationally recognized
            rights and standards. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>For humanitarian actors </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Treat harmful information management as an operational risk &#8211; not just
            a communications challenge &#8211; integrated into humanitarian diplomacy and protection
            dialogue with states, regional organizations and multilateral forums; and into
            programmes, risk frameworks and preparedness planning. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Train staff and volunteers in rumour verification, digital literacy and safe
            information programmes; share insights across trusted organizations. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Strengthen monitoring by combining AI-enabled tools with human expertise for
            real-time detection, mapping of harmful information ecosystems and early warning; foster
            collaboration across the humanitarian sector to pool resources and capacity. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Document and analyse harmful information incidents systematically to build
            an evidence base for policy, adaptation and advocacy. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Engage communities transparently, co-creating messages with affected
            communities and reinforcing neutrality, impartiality and independence. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>For communities and local leaders </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Develop and sustain local rumour-tracking and verification systems. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Act as trusted intermediaries to strengthen solidarity, resilience and
            public confidence in humanitarian response. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Provide feedback loops to humanitarian actors and authorities on trust gaps
            and unmet concerns. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Ensure inclusivity, by making sure youth, minorities and people with
            disabilities, are represented in community information systems. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Foster dialogue, peer-to-peer engagement and communityled initiatives to
            counter harmful narratives and prevent polarization or stigma. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h1>Trust, truth and preparedness </h1>
        <normal>We are already living through an information crisis. Future emergency preparedness
            must include equitable access to reliable information, supported by early warning and
            systems that serve all communities, especially the most at risk. Harmful information is
            not only eroding trust in humanitarian action, it is fuelling societal division and
            undermining cooperation at a time when unity is urgently needed to face global
            challenges. </normal>
        <normal>Trust is critical to the legitimacy, effectiveness and acceptance of humanitarian
            action. This was strongly emphasized at the 2019 International Conference of the Red
            Cross and Red Crescent Movement which recognized<regular-italic> </regular-italic>that
            trust in principled humanitarian action is indispensable to serving at-risk people and
            encouraged all members of the conference to act to preserve and develop this trust.
            Crucially, trust in humanitarian action does not rest solely on humanitarian actors. It
            also depends on a conducive environment &#8211; one in which principled, effective and
            accountable action is actively supported. Such an environment is shaped by the legal,
            political and operational frameworks established by states and other actors. This
            includes respect for humanitarian principles, flexible and needs-based funding,
            protection of humanitarian access and clear delineation of roles and responsibilities of
            various actors. </normal>
        <normal>In an era of increasing volumes of harmful information and rising public distrust,
            humanitarian organizations face a growing challenge: principled, fact-based
            communication often struggles to compete with emotionally charged narratives, polarizing
            content and opinion-driven discourse. Even when &#8211; perhaps especially when &#8211;
            grounded in evidence and neutrality, humanitarian messaging is often drowned out by
            louder, more emotionally resonant voices, particularly online. This creates a
            significant perception challenge. Trust and integrity may be questioned and principles
            seen as detached from realities or lacking empathy. </normal>
        <normal>The result is a trust and perception problem: neutrality, facts and rationality are
            increasingly misunderstood or mistrusted. When emotion and polarization drive
            engagement, even well-intentioned communications risk being reframed as political or
            partial. This distorts how communities perceive humanitarian work and undermines the
            credibility of those committed to principled humanitarian action. Navigating this
            landscape requires sustained community engagement, especially offline, where dialogue
            can foster proximity and trust. Digitally, it may also involve recognizing the limits of
            engagement and, in some cases, closing comment sections or refraining from responding
            when dialogue cannot be conducted in good faith. </normal>
        <normal>Among the seven Fundamental Principles of the International Red Cross and Red
            Crescent Movement, neutrality and impartiality are often the least understood and
            provoke the most controversy. This is somewhat ironic, given that neutrality&#8217;s
            purpose is precisely to avoid entanglement in controversy. At its core, neutrality is
            not an end in itself, but a method to preserve trust and access in polarized or
            politicized environments. Impartiality, meanwhile, demands that aid be provided solely
            based on need, without discrimination of any kind. Together, these principles safeguard
            the Movement&#8217;s ability to serve at-risk populations equitably and without bias. </normal>
        <normal>In such a fragmented and contested information space, the voices of affected
            populations risk being drowned out, distorted or co-opted. Trust cannot be demanded; it
            must be built through repeated action, transparency, accountability and integrity.
            Resilience against harmful information requires more than just correcting falsehoods, it
            requires sustained engagement, openness and meaningful participation. Humanitarian
            organizations must also actively communicate who they are, what they do, their impact
            and why they act &#8211; making a clear, compelling case for principled humanitarian
            action and for preserving a neutral and impartial humanitarian space, free from
            political influence. Despite the barriers posed by polarized perceptions, principled
            humanitarian organizations can maintain &#8211; and even rebuild &#8211; trust and
            acceptance in the face of harmful information. Looking ahead, a critical question is
            whether trust and proximity at the community level can serve as a <bold>firewall </bold>against
            the spread or impact of harmful information. </normal>
        <normal>Responding to harmful information requires more than increasing the volume of
            communication or correcting falsehoods. These approaches alone do not build trust and
            can even backfire, particularly during armed conflicts, political unrest or situations
            marked by discrimination. Effective responses go beyond countering narratives; they
            focus on disrupting harmful information and strengthening resilience at both
            organizational and societal levels. Trust is built through proximity, understanding,
            access to services and a sense of shared ownership. Crucially, it cannot be created in
            the middle of a crisis; it must be cultivated over time.<fig
                href_fmt="images/p-SYR2114-AB_fmt.jpg" href="file://images/p-SYR2114-AB.tif"></fig>
        </normal>
        <h1-recommendations>Asks, aims and recommendations </h1-recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Asks </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Place trust at the centre of humanitarian action by ensuring that the
            principles of <bold>rights, dignity, inclusivity, accountability, transparency and
            feedback</bold> guide how organizations communicate and engage with communities.</recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Aims </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Reduce uncertainty through timely, transparent and consistent communication
            and engagement before, during and after crises. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Strengthen legitimacy and accountability by aligning with community
            priorities and tracking trust. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Protect staff and volunteers with safeguards, skills and inclusive
            engagement to operate safely in contested information spaces. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Empower communities: Build two-way feedback and participation systems that
            allow people to voice concerns, influence decisions and counter harmful narratives. </recommendations>
        <h3>Recommendations </h3>
        <h4>For governments and policy-makers </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Establish rights-based policy frameworks that safeguard access to reliable
            information in humanitarian crises. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Embed trust-building into crisis preparedness and response plans. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Invest in early warning and monitoring systems to detect and counter harmful
            narratives. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Support National Societies in their auxiliary role ensuring independence,
            impartiality, neutrality and integrity are respected. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Ensure rapid rebuttals of falsehoods that threaten humanitarian access,
            action and security. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>For technology platforms </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Detect and mitigate harmful content that undermines humanitarian action and
            trust. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Share relevant data and insights safely with humanitarian actors to support
            real-time response. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Ensure moderation, fact-checking and AI tools work in low-bandwidth,
            multilingual environments. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Collaborate with humanitarian actors on verification and labelling
            mechanisms to amplify credible content. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>For humanitarian actors </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Develop policies, guidelines, standards and metrics (e.g., Community Trust
            Index and community engagement and accountability) to measure and track trust and
            harmful information, and guide responses. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Embed trust as an operational asset across preparedness, response and
            recovery. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Communicate transparently and inclusively, correcting falsehoods rapidly and
            co-creating messages with communities. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Train staff and volunteers in rumour management, digital safety (including
            protection from online harassment) and culturally sensitive engagement. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Strengthen real-time analysis of and response to community feedback,
            adapting visibly to concerns, demonstrating impact and sharing lessons learned to build
            collective resilience. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>For communities and local leaders </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Act as trusted intermediaries by amplifying verified information and
            countering rumours. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Partner with humanitarian actors to co-create rumour-tracking and
            verification systems. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Sustain trust through dialogue in schools, faith institutions and community
            centres. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Engage in participatory feedback and research to ensure that responses
            reflect local priorities.</bullet-list-2c>
        <h1>Navigating humanitarian action in a post-trust information era </h1>
        <normal>Humanitarian action now unfolds within a highly contested information environment,
            characterized by Barclay as a &#8216;post-trust culture,&#8217; where truth plays a
            diminished role in shaping human decision-making. In this environment, technology
            amplifies and instrumentalizes information, allowing harmful narratives to spread
            quickly, especially where reliable information is scarce. </normal>
        <normal>Climate change, vaccine hesitancy and migration are among the issues on which
            harmful information thrives, crossing borders and continually being reshaped by local
            contexts, narratives and political agendas. These same issues also contribute to
            humanitarian crises. Humanitarian organizations therefore face a delicate balancing act:
            they must meet urgent needs while navigating what can and cannot be said, avoiding
            controversies that could inflame tensions or compromise perceptions of neutrality. </normal>
        <normal>At the heart of this challenge lies the power of narrative. Narratives shape how
            people interpret information and decide whom to trust and whether to engage with
            humanitarian actors. They are reinforced by lived experience, public discourse, media
            coverage and digital engagement. When there is a gap between dominant narratives and
            people&#8217;s daily realities, trust erodes and alternative or harmful narratives often
            emerge. These narratives frequently define identity by portraying certain individuals or
            groups as outsiders, threats or illegitimate &#8211; as the &#8216;other&#8217;. Such
            framing generates fear, fuels exclusion, dehumanizes and normalizes hostility. For
            example, displaced populations may be cast not as victims of a crisis but as threats to
            national stability or competition for scarce resources. In this way, narrative shapes
            perception and the notion of the &#8216;other&#8217; shapes belonging &#8211; who is
            trusted or untrusted, legitimate or illegitimate. </normal>
        <normal>Narratives also simplify complexity, evoke emotion and may weaken social cohesion.<regular-italic> </regular-italic>In today&#8217;s information ecosystem, humanitarian organizations
            must contend not only with physical threats but also with digital and cyber ones. They
            are increasingly framed as ineffective responders, political tools or even foreign
            agents. This makes it harder to ensure that accurate, trusted information reaches the
            people who need it most and can be distinguished from harmful content. In contested or
            sensitive environments, people may instead turn to online communities for answers
            &#8211; even when these communities amplify harmful messaging driven by actors lacking
            expertise and clear political or economic agendas. </normal>
        <normal>Malicious actors exploit people&#8217;s limited capacity to process information by
            amplifying feelings of fear, grievance and crisis. This does not just create short-term
            confusion; it entrenches long-term mistrust. The consequences are real. Harmful
            narratives influence how communities perceive risk, how they respond during emergencies
            and how they prepare for future shocks, including disasters. In moments of crisis,
            harmful narratives can fuel denial, panic or resistance &#8211; ultimately undermining
            life-saving interventions. </normal>
        <h1-recommendations>Asks, aims and recommendations </h1-recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Asks<bold> </bold></normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Strengthen global cooperation on platform accountability, AI governance and
            the protection of humanitarian information by embedding <bold>human rights,
                preparedness, accountability and collaboration</bold> into legal and policy
            frameworks. Invest in community-led resilience, preparedness and feedback systems that
            empower all community members, ensure access to information and protect vulnerable
            populations &#8211; applying a clear rights-based approach in practice. </recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Aims </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Prevent harmful information from undermining humanitarian access and
            action. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Strengthen community resilience: equip communities and volunteers with
            trusted information, preparedness tools and locally grounded strategies to counter
            harmful narratives. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Advance policy coherence by embedding humanitarian perspectives in digital
            and AI governance. </recommendations>
        <h3>Recommendations </h3>
        <h4>States and policy-makers </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Champion the protection of humanitarian information within legal and policy
            frameworks for AI governance and platform accountability. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Counter harmful narratives that stigmatize communities and/or principled
            humanitarian organizations, while avoiding the politicization of humanitarian action. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Reaffirm the importance of safe, unhindered humanitarian access and promote
            understanding of humanitarian mandates, including the auxiliary role of National
            Societies as independent yet recognized partners to public authorities. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Engage with humanitarian actors to ensure timely, accurate and locally
            relevant communication strategies that support humanitarian action. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Ensure national information laws and policies comply with international law. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Technology platforms </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Provide locally adapted tools, including multilingual translation,
            culturally relevant fact-checking and accessibility features. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Amplify verified humanitarian information in crises by engaging with
            humanitarian and community actors. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Monitor how humanitarian narratives are reshaped locally and mitigate
            harmful reinterpretations. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Adapt and/or cool algorithms during crises to reduce amplification of
            harmful narratives. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Strengthen partnerships with humanitarian organizations and community media
            to ensure reliable, timely and life-saving messages reach affected populations. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Humanitarian actors </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Co-create inclusive, locally relevant messages with communities, journalists
            and trusted influencers for contextual, cultural and linguistic relevance. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Monitor perceptions of humanitarian action and adapt real-time messaging
            across online and offline channels. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Build resilience through training, capacity building and embedding harmful
            information management in humanitarian diplomacy, risk and behaviour change. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Document and share insights and lessons learned on combating harmful
            information to support continuous adaptation and strengthen collective resilience. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Community and local leaders </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Contextualize and disseminate verified humanitarian information in ways that
            reflect community priorities. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Use peer networks, dialogue and community-led initiatives to challenge
            harmful information. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Identify trust gaps and communicate concerns directly to humanitarian actors
            and authorities.</bullet-list-2c>
        <h1>Navigating a hostile information landscape </h1>
        <normal>Harmful information is not an abstract threat: it has direct, tangible consequences
            for humanitarian operations, often in ways that undermine trust, disrupt access and
            endanger both staff and affected communities. From false accusations to targeted
            campaigns, humanitarian actors across the globe are increasingly confronted with the
            operational fallout of distorted narratives. These impacts are being felt in armed
            conflicts, during public health emergencies, in disaster responses and in the everyday
            functioning of humanitarian organizations, whether local or international. </normal>
        <normal>Virtual spaces are not neutral arenas for dialogue. Digital platforms have become
            battlegrounds where trust and truth are deliberately undermined and where individuals,
            communities and even nations are subjected to harmful information attacks. In this
            dense, volatile space, the boundaries between truth and falsehood blur. Humanitarian
            narratives must contend with an overwhelming flood of emotional, politicized and
            sometimes instrumentalized content. </normal>
        <normal>A decade ago, there was a sense that the &#8220;information flows cannot be
            controlled nor do they need to be&#8221;. This perspective reflected an earlier digital
            era, when social media platforms were emerging and user-generated content largely
            reflected the goodwill of individuals, rather than the calculated harmful intent of
            malicious actors. At the time, it was a progressive call for greater participation,
            transparency and accountability. But today&#8217;s landscape is profoundly different.
            The question is no longer whether information should be regulated, but what should be
            addressed, how, by whom and with what safeguards &#8211; particularly in terms of
            protecting fundamental rights and freedoms. Striking this balance has become one of the
            central challenges of the current era. </normal>
        <normal>At its core, humanitarian action is about meeting the needs of people in crises, not
            securing visibility or reputation of the organizations delivering it. Yet, when the
            spotlight shifts from communities and onto organizations &#8211; through unmerited
            criticism or targeted harmful information &#8211; their safety and ability to operate
            effectively is under threat. Increasingly, harmful narratives shape public and societal
            perceptions of humanitarian action, constrain access, erode trust and shrink the
            operational space for principled humanitarian action. While legitimate scrutiny is vital
            for accountability and improvement, it must be distinguished from deliberate distortion
            or harmful disinformation designed to delegitimize and obstruct humanitarian efforts.
            The consequences, as highlighted throughout this report, are stark: diminished access,
            reputational damage, emotional strain and heightened security threats to staff and
            volunteers, operational delays and loss of public trust. </normal>
        <normal>These dynamics underscore the urgent need for more coordinated and systemic
            responses. Addressing harmful information requires sector-wide collaboration and
            investment, and proactive engagement with those who shape and influence the information
            environment &#8211; not least governments and technology companies (see Chapter 5 for a
            detailed examination of their role). </normal>
        <normal>Above all, this landscape raises urgent questions that no single organization can
            resolve alone: the challenges transcend the mandate or influence of any individual
            organization. The dilemmas demand collective reflection and shared approaches: </normal>
        <numbered-list><bold>Neutrality versus harmful narratives: </bold>When dehumanizing or
            discriminatory narratives spread &#8211; sometimes by state or political actors &#8211;
            should humanitarians remain silent to preserve neutrality and access, or speak out to
            prevent harm? </numbered-list>
        <numbered-list><bold>Debunking versus risking access: </bold>Should falsehoods be publicly
            challenged, even if doing so risks undermining neutrality or operational access? How can
            humanitarian actors respond without being drawn into politicized or polarized debates? </numbered-list>
        <numbered-list><bold>Integrity versus polarization: </bold>In fragmented and hostile
            information environments, how can humanitarian actors protect the integrity of their
            messaging and maintain trust without being co-opted, misrepresented or silenced? </numbered-list>
        <numbered-list><bold>Collective action versus fragmented responses: </bold>What
            partnerships, mechanisms and international norms are needed to protect humanitarian
            organizations from information attacks? Should the sector advocate collectively for
            stronger platform policies and governance frameworks to safeguard humanitarian space? </numbered-list>
        <numbered-list><bold>Speak out versus silence: </bold>When harmful narratives systematically
            target groups in vulnerable situations &#8211; such as migrants &#8211; and are driven
            by state or political interests, what space remains for humanitarians to respond? How
            can they challenge such narratives without compromising neutrality? At what point is
            silence perceived as tacit approval of discriminatory or dehumanizing narratives, and
            when does silence risk becoming complicity? </numbered-list>
        <normal>Together, these dilemmas underscore the urgent need for the humanitarian sector to
            find collective strategies that preserve principled humanitarian action while protecting
            at-risk groups and safeguarding trust in an increasingly hostile information
            environment.<fig href_fmt="images/v-LBN0533-AB_fmt.jpg"
                href="file://images/v-LBN0533-AB.tif"></fig>
        </normal>
        <h1-recommendations>Asks, aims and recommendations </h1-recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Asks </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Treat harmful information as an operational risk by embedding <bold>preparedness,
            accountability and transparency</bold> into all phases of humanitarian action, from
            early warning to recovery &#8211; and measure its human, social and operational harms as
            rigorously as physical impacts. </recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Aims </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Safeguard humanitarian access and action by recognizing harmful information
            as a systemic risk. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Protect operations, staff and community trust: integrate harmful
            information analysis and response into all phases of humanitarian action. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Build resilience by resourcing responses and systematically measuring harms
            to inform evidence-based action. </recommendations>
        <h3>Recommendations </h3>
        <h4>States and policy-makers </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Build societal resilience through public information literacy and awareness
            initiatives. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Integrate harmful information risks into disaster management and
            crisis-response frameworks. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Support mechanisms to identify and address harmful information incidents
            that endanger civilians or disrupt humanitarian operations, ensuring the mandates of
            principled humanitarian actors are respected. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Support international cooperation and uphold cyber norms to protect
            humanitarian action and critical services. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Establish flexible funding lines for harmful information response, with
            priority for building local resilience and community-led rumour tracking. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Technology platforms </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Adapt or &#8216;cool&#8217; algorithms during humanitarian crises to reduce
            amplification of harmful narratives. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Prioritize authoritative information from trusted humanitarian, health and
            local actors to deliver timely and life-saving guidance. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Implement crisis protocols that temporarily re-weight algorithms in favour
            of safety and reliability over optimizing engagement. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Collaborate with principled humanitarian actors to design context-specific,
            transparent interventions on platforms that respect users&#8217; human rights and
            protect the safety of crisis-affected populations. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Ensure independent oversight to balance freedom of expression with the need
            to prevent harm to civilians, humanitarian actors and operations. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Humanitarian actors </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Integrate harmful information monitoring into programmes, assessments and
            early warning systems. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Document, analyse and share actionable insights and lessons learned from
            harmful information incidents and their operational impacts to inform real-time
            adaptation and long-term resilience, without impeding principled humanitarian action. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Strengthen staff and volunteer capacity to identify, document and respond
            safely to harmful narratives. Strengthen internal communication systems to ensure staff
            and volunteers are informed, coordinated and able to respond safely and consistently to
            harmful narratives while upholding humanitarian principles. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Invest in multilingual monitoring, two-way communication, rapid verification
            systems and partnerships with trusted local moderators. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Facilitate regional research hubs to strengthen monitoring, measurement and
            evidence-based assessment of harms. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Strengthen collaboration and training for humanitarian staff and volunteers
            on digital threats, information and media literacy, and narrative analysis. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Community and local leaders </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Co-create rumour-tracking and feedback systems to detect harmful information
            early. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Verify and amplify accurate information through trusted local channels. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Document harmful information incidents that affect safety, services or
            access. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Foster dialogue and peer-to-peer engagement that reduces stigma, fear and
            division.</bullet-list-2c>
        <h1>A collective responsibility for preserving principled humanitarian action </h1>
        <normal>Harmful information is borderless, adaptive and often directed at the people most at
            risk. Algorithmic systems amplify its spread, while global disparities in data
            governance, AI capacity and political and societal polarization intensify its reach.
            Effective responses require greater algorithmic transparency on how content is sorted,
            ranked, amplified and targeted, combined with approaches that protect privacy, dignity
            and authenticity. </normal>
        <normal-expanded>Humanitarian crises &#8211; from pandemics to armed conflict &#8211; create
            fertile ground for harmful information. Information related to the COVID-19 pandemic
            exposed both the speed of harmful information spread and the cost of delayed action.
            Meeting the challenges of identifying, preventing and mitigating harmful information
            requires a systems approach and urgent, cross-sectoral action. Fragmentation between
            humanitarian actors, digital rights advocates and the technology communities must be
            bridged. This includes creating space for emerging questions, fostering diverse and
            underrepresented perspectives, and prioritizing principles and accountability. Strong,
            forward-looking partnerships are essential, not only to shape governance frameworks, but
            to influence the design and deployment of tools used to navigate this rapidly evolving
            landscape. </normal-expanded>
        <normal>Determining what constitutes harmful information is essential for any entity seeking
            to develop a strategic response aligned with risk management. The impact of harmful
            information depends on several variables including its scope (scale and severity),
            duration, magnitude of the incident and the resilience of the affected individual,
            organization and broader context. Harm may result directly from the incident or
            indirectly, with distinctions often based on the degree of certainty that the
            information caused the outcome. A single incident can generate multiple forms of harm,
            classified as direct (primary) or indirect (secondary or tertiary). These may include
            physical, psychological, societal and deprivational harms. The effects of harmful
            information are often disruptive and multidimensional, manifesting across several
            categories simultaneously. </normal>
        <normal>One of the most contested areas in defining harmful information is the boundary
            between legitimate political dissent and incitement. In some contexts, this line is
            blurred, raising serious concerns about freedom of expression. Content may be labelled
            as dissenting, destabilizing or inciting violence, particularly during times of crisis
            or internal tension. The challenge is ensuring that measures designed to counter harmful
            information are not used as a pretext for silencing dissent. Clear safeguards are needed
            to distinguish between speech that challenges authority and speech that genuinely
            threatens public order, safety and human dignity. </normal>
        <normal>Resilience must be built at every level &#8211; individual, institutional and
            societal &#8211; drawing on community trust, local knowledge, behavioural science,
            digital and information literacy. Evidence shows that simple interventions, such as
            digital prompts, can reduce the sharing of false content, underscoring the value of
            pairing regulation with context-specific solutions. Governments, platforms, civil
            society and researchers must work together to test and scale what works. This
            underscores the importance of pairing regulation with behavioural science and practical
            interventions that are context specific. Governments, platforms, civil society and
            researchers must work together to test what works, for whom and in which context. </normal>
        <normal>For the humanitarian sector, strengthening cross-sector engagement is essential
            &#8211; not only to ensure the flow of trustworthy information but also to identify and
            respond to harmful information. Disruption alone is not enough. Responding effectively
            requires a collective effort such as building on that initiated for global health
            security during the COVID-19 pandemic. </normal>
        <normal>Ultimately, states must act. As underscored in the Movement&#8217;s Appeal to
            States, addressing harmful information is now central to principled humanitarian action.
            Trusted information may not be water, food or shelter but it is imperative to accessing
            all three, as well as to ensuring safety, dignity and autonomy. </normal>
        <t1-definition>Appeal to States</t1-definition>
        <normal-definition-first>The 2024 Council of Delegates called on states to take all
            appropriate measures to address harmful information.<regular-italic> </regular-italic></normal-definition-first>
        <quote>We appeal to States to take all appropriate measures to prevent, stop and remedy any
            abuse, pressure, misinformation, disinformation and dehumanizing rhetoric, through
            social media or otherwise, that harms the physical, psychological or reputational
            wellbeing of people in vulnerable situations and the staff and volunteers of the
            Movement components serving them.&#8221;<fig
                href_fmt="images/JOINT_OPENING_CEREMONY_(16)-AB_fmt.jpg"
                href="file://images/JOINT_OPENING_CEREMONY_(16)-AB.tif"></fig>
        </quote>
        <h1-recommendations>Asks, aims and recommendations </h1-recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Asks </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Balance the protection of humanitarian space, the safety and dignity of
            affected populations and the integrity of humanitarian operations with freedom of
            expression by building rights-respecting, transparent, accountable and resilient
            information ecosystems. </recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Aims </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Ensure laws and policies protect principled humanitarian action and
            safeguard trusted and reliable information. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Hold platforms accountable for measures that protect principled
            humanitarian action and implement transparent, rights-respecting crisis protocols that
            safeguard affected populations and humanitarian personnel. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Embed harmful information analysis into humanitarian operations to
            safeguard trust, access and principled humanitarian action. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Engage affected communities in information strategies and work with digital
            platforms to ensure timely, accurate and safe information flow. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Build trusted information ecosystems through digital and media literacy,
            local dialogue, initiatives that counter polarization and ongoing monitoring to evaluate
            and adapt interventions. </recommendations>
        <h3>Recommendations </h3>
        <h4>States and policy-makers </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Adopt rights-respecting regulations to counter harmful information while
            safeguarding humanitarian action and trusted information. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Coordinate with humanitarian actors to ensure laws and regulations protect
            and respect principled humanitarian action. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Integrate risks from harmful information that could affect principled
            humanitarian action into negotiations, frameworks and operational planning. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Respect and support the independence of National Societies in their
            auxiliary role ensuring they can operate without interference. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Regulators and technology companies </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>In humanitarian crises, report transparently on harmful content removal,
            moderation practices and algorithmic adjustments to ensure trust, accountability and
            prevent harm to people in need and humanitarian personnel and volunteers. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Collaborate with principled humanitarian actors to design localized
            mitigation tools such as fact-check bots, verified information hubs and multilingual
            content. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Strengthen enforcement against coordinated harmful information campaigns
            targeting principled humanitarian organizations and the safety and dignity of affected
            communities, humanitarian personnel and volunteers. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Develop and apply rights-respecting crisis-response protocols in
            collaboration with humanitarian actors and share relevant data with humanitarian
            organizations and research hubs to support trusted, principled action. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Humanitarian actors </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Embed trusted information as essential for principled humanitarian action
            and for combating harmful information into humanitarian standards and operational
            frameworks. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Share evidence of harmful information trends with regulators and platforms
            in ways that respect data protection rules and support principled humanitarian action to
            mitigate harmful information, protect humanitarian action, and safeguard affected
            populations, humanitarian personnel and volunteers. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Partner with local journalists, fact-checkers and trusted content creators
            to amplify accurate, contextualized and life-saving information for populations in need. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Strengthen community engagement by integrating media literacy, information
            resilience and feedback mechanisms into humanitarian programming, ensuring communities
            can access, understand and act on reliable information. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Communities and local leaders </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Promote community-based media and independent journalism to provide timely,
            accurate and accessible information. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Lead digital and media literacy initiatives to build critical thinking and
            resilience to harmful information. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Act as trusted intermediaries by disseminating verified information through
            local channels such as radio, schools and faith institutions. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Facilitate dialogue to counter polarization, address stigma and prevent
            harmful information from escalating into violence. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h1>From communication to collaboration </h1>
        <normal>In an era marked by record-breaking climate extremes, a growing number of disasters
            and emergencies and shrinking humanitarian budgets, the imperative to act to prepare
            before crises strike has never been more critical. But today&#8217;s emergencies are not
            only physical &#8211; they are also informational. Harmful information can amplify fear,
            erode trust and disrupt preparedness and response efforts. It exacerbates existing
            vulnerabilities and tensions, compounding risks in contexts where trust is already
            fragile. As with disaster risk reduction, addressing harmful information requires a
            fundamental shift from reactive response to proactive resilience. This means supporting
            locally led action, investing ahead of crises and tackling the root causes of risk at
            the heart of humanitarian strategies. </normal>
        <normal>Just as physical disasters need not be deadly or destabilizing if communities are
            supported to anticipate, withstand and adapt, the same holds for harmful information.
            The challenge lies in scaling and sustaining locally grounded solutions by embedding
            information resilience into humanitarian programming. Strengthening resilience through
            integrated, cross-sectoral approaches shifts the focus from reacting to harmful
            information crises to managing risks and building communities able to withstand them. </normal>
        <normal>Addressing harmful information effectively requires more than delivering messages,
            it demands a fundamental shift in mindset: from disseminating information to enable
            participation and agency. Too often, communication efforts are designed as one-way
            flows, with external actors determining what information is relevant or important, how
            it is framed and who gets to speak. This top-down approach not only risks reinforcing
            existing power imbalances but also overlooks the insights, lived experiences and
            priorities of people in need. </normal>
        <normal>In contrast, when communities are actively involved in shaping the narratives,
            identifying risks and driving the response, they are no longer passive recipients of
            information but co-creators of solutions. Building resilience to harmful information is
            not simply about correcting falsehoods &#8211; it is about restoring trust, deepening
            dialogue and empowering people to navigate information environments. </normal>
        <normal>This shift toward shared agency requires: </normal>
        <bullet-list><bold>Recognizing and supporting trusted local actors</bold>, from youth
            leaders and women&#8217;s groups to religious figures and community media, who are best
            positioned to engage meaningfully with their peers and people in need. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list><bold>Investing in local information ecosystems</bold> &#8211; community radio,
            local journalists, digital access points, feedback mechanisms &#8211; that provide
            continuous, context-relevant communication before, during and after crises. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list><bold>Embedding media and digital literacy into humanitarian programming</bold>,
            enabling individuals to assess and challenge harmful content and engage in informed
            decision-making. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list><bold>Creating space for participatory content creation</bold>, allowing
            communities to express their perspectives in formats that resonate culturally and
            emotionally, whether through storytelling, theatre, radio or social media. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list><bold>Safeguarding community engagement</bold>, ensuring that participation
            does not expose individuals to risks, especially in politically polarized or fragile
            environments. </bullet-list>
        <normal>As highlighted throughout this report, harmful information is not just a
            communications challenge, it is a threat to humanitarian access, acceptance and
            security, and as such requires a whole-of-organization and whole-of-society approach.
            Addressing it requires systems thinking, sustained collaboration and a willingness to
            share control. Just as humanitarian actors need to fully embrace the localization agenda
            in service delivery, the same commitment is needed in response to harmful information:
            to listen, co-create and build responses grounded in trust, transparency and mutual
            accountability. </normal>
        <normal>The critical elements of strategic communication in a digital age &#8211; the right
            audience, right message, right time and right messenger &#8211; are especially important
            in efforts to counter harmful information. These four components are deeply
            interdependent. </normal>
        <normal>Ultimately, resilience to harmful information is not achieved through better
            messaging &#8211; it is built through better relationships. By investing in local
            voices, community ownership and inclusive approaches, the humanitarian sector can move
            beyond reactive counter-narratives and toward a more sustainable, principled and
            people-centred response. Shifting toward shared agency means recognizing that trust and
            legitimacy come not from broadcasting facts, but from meaningful participation, dialogue
            and mutual accountability.<fig href_fmt="images/p-CMR481-AB_fmt.jpg"
                href="file://images/p-CMR481-AB.tif"></fig>
        </normal>
        <h1-recommendations>Asks, aims and recommendations </h1-recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Asks </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Put communities at the heart of information resilience by investing in<regular-italic> </regular-italic><bold>inclusivity, accountability and collaboration. </bold>This
            includes supporting<regular-italic> </regular-italic>feedback mechanisms, local
            verification and community-owned narratives that strengthen locally trusted information
            systems, enabling principled humanitarian action and more effective crisis response. </recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Aims </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Strengthen principled humanitarian action by embedding community voices and
            verification systems within information ecosystems. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Ensure humanitarian responses are principled and accountable by using
            information and narratives grounded in local perspectives, reflecting diverse community
            voices, and promoting trust and inclusivity in decision-making. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Strengthen operational resilience by ensuring diverse voices guide
            humanitarian decisions and responses. </recommendations>
        <h3>Recommendations </h3>
        <h4>States and policy-makers </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Resource community-led verification and communication by funding
            rumour-tracking, independent journalism and inclusive channels (radio, digital access
            points, offline formats) in local languages. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Strengthen information ecosystems<bold> </bold>critical to humanitarian
            action<bold> </bold>by investing in local capacity and information literacy, and
            promoting stronger responses from technology platforms and proactive measures to counter
            harmful information. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Empower trusted local actors &#8211; including youth groups, women&#8217;s
            networks and community media &#8211; through partnerships, resources and safeguards, and
            integrate them into local information ecosystems to support verification, feedback and
            principled humanitarian action during crises. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Humanitarian actors </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Build accountability and trust through co-created messages, community
            feedback loops, transparent reporting and joint review with communities &#8211; ensuring
            that engagement respects humanitarian principles and avoids politicization. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Establish early warning and rapid response systems to monitor information
            patterns and narratives that affect humanitarian action, amplify trusted messengers and
            enable timely responses at the local level &#8211; while safeguarding privacy. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Support community-led content by enabling safe, independent storytelling and
            locally relevant information in local languages, with robust safeguarding measures to
            protect contributors and ensure inclusion. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Strengthen local journalists and media through capacity building for timely
            and accessible multilingual content across both online and offline platforms &#8211;
            while maintaining neutrality and avoiding alignment with political agendas &#8211; to
            support principled humanitarian crisis response and a resilient local information
            ecosystem. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Measure and learn by tracking trust, participation quality, the inclusion of
            marginalized voices and timeliness of corrections &#8211; using anonymized or aggregated
            data &#8211; and share lessons learned to improve principled humanitarian responses
            across contexts. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Ensure strategic communication in humanitarian contexts aligns the right
            audience, message, timing and messenger, recognizing their interdependence, to
            effectively counter harmful information and support principled, context-sensitive
            responses. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Communities and local leaders </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Generate and amplify community-owned narratives that build trust and support
            principled humanitarian action during crises. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Act as trusted intermediaries facilitating &#8211; where required &#8211;
            dialogue between humanitarian actors, authorities and populations in need to ensure
            two-way accountability and respecting and supporting the role of principled humanitarian
            organizations. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Safeguard inclusivity in local information systems so that diverse voices
            &#8211; including groups that are marginalized &#8211; are represented and heard.</bullet-list-2c>
        <h1>Principled action requires more than declarations </h1>
        <normal>In an information environment distorted by rumour, manipulation and politically
            charged content, trust in humanitarian actors is increasingly fragile. Harmful
            information can undermine the perceived impartiality, neutrality and independence of
            humanitarian actors, fuel suspicion among communities and endanger staff, volunteers and
            the people they serve. In the sentiment-driven economy of social media and now AI,
            principled humanitarian action is easily misunderstood or misrepresented &#8211;
            especially when it fails to align with dominant political or emotional narratives. In
            such settings, the consistent application of humanitarian principles becomes not only
            more difficult but more essential. </normal>
        <normal>There is a growing strategic vulnerability: humanitarian action is designed to be
            deliberate, impartial and context specific. Digital information, by contrast, is
            immediate, emotional and virally amplified. This creates a dangerous speed mismatch.
            Humanitarian actors generally take time to verify facts, assess needs and coordinate
            responses. Harmful narratives and outrage, by contrast, travel in seconds &#8211;
            unconcerned with humanity, neutrality, accuracy, proportionality or consequence. </normal>
        <normal>Declaring adherence to the fundamental and humanitarian principles is not enough.
            Access to affected populations and acceptance of humanitarian actors must be continually
            earned. They depend on humility, principled behaviour, operational effectiveness and
            impact, and timely, transparent engagement and communication. Words must align with
            actions. Without this alignment, safe and sustained access &#8211; essential for
            principled humanitarian action &#8211; becomes increasingly difficult to secure. </normal>
        <normal>Upholding humanitarian principles today means more than silent adherence. It
            requires actively promoting, explaining and embodying them in every context &#8211;
            including the digital sphere, where harmful information and politicized narratives
            quickly erode trust. </normal>
        <normal>In an era of accelerating technology, human responses such as empathy, respect and
            moral restraint are more critical than ever. As philosopher Jonathan Glover observed,
            these moral resources help people exercise self-restraint, respect the dignity of others
            and care for their suffering and well-being. He described them as &#8220;the tendency to
            respond to people with certain kinds of respect &#8211; as members of our community, as
            human beings&#8221; and as &#8220;sympathy &#8211; caring about the miseries and the
            happiness of others, and perhaps feeling a degree of identification with them.&#8221; </normal>
        <normal>Today, harmful information is not a communication challenge; it is a threat to
            humanitarian action and requires a whole-of-society and whole-of-organization approach.
            Where humanitarian communicators once focused on facilitating information sharing with
            affected communities and on engaging donors, they are now increasingly tasked with
            detecting, responding to and trying to mitigate harmful content. Yet many organizations
            remain underprepared for the scale and sophistication of today&#8217;s information
            threats. </normal>
        <normal>Technology can undoubtedly streamline humanitarian operations, but it also raises
            difficult questions about whether it risks dehumanizing humanitarian action &#8211;
            replacing listening with automation or judgement with algorithmic logic. Writing in
            1999, long before today&#8217;s digital transformation, Glover presciently concluded in
            his book <regular-italic>Humanity</regular-italic>: </normal>
        <normal>&#8220;It is too late to stop the technology. It is to the psychology that we should
            now turn.&#8221; </normal>
        <normal>Glover is saying that the danger lies less in the machines themselves than in how
            human psychology responds to the power they give us. The survival of humanity depends
            not on stopping technology, but on understanding and strengthening the moral psychology
            that restrains its misuse. In today&#8217;s landscape, where trust is fragile and
            harmful information can undo principled efforts in moments, this call is more urgent
            than ever. Just as Glover emphasizes that moral restraint and psychology are central
            once technology cannot be stopped, the Movement Appeal to States underscores that
            humanitarian principles &#8211; humanity, neutrality, impartiality and independence
            &#8211; serve as psychological and ethical safeguards in complex and high-pressure
            environments. In a polarized information landscape, where narratives can manipulate
            perception and inflame divisions, adherence to these principles acts as a moral and
            operational compass, guiding actors to resist pressures, make impartial decisions, and
            maintain trust. Essentially, <bold>while we cannot control the speed or reach of harmful
            information (the &#8216;technology&#8217;), we can rely on principled humanitarian
                action (the &#8216;psychology&#8217;) </bold>to ensure that responses remain
            ethical, impartial, and focused on human need. In today&#8217;s landscape, where trust
            is fragile and harmful information can undo principled efforts in moments, his call is
            more urgent than ever. </normal>
        <normal>As harmful narratives accelerate while communication about humanitarian action lags,
            the sector faces declining trust and shrinking operational space. Addressing this
            challenge requires confronting these dilemmas directly and adapting communication
            practices to keep pace with the evolving information environment. </normal>
        <normal>If trust is rooted in vulnerability and expectation, humanity is grounded in respect
            and compassion. The principle of humanity is widely recognized as the foundational
            driver of humanitarian action. It is what compels humanitarian actors to act: to save
            lives, reduce suffering and uphold the dignity of people affected by crises. Among the
            core humanitarian principles, humanity is superior to the others because it captures the
            moral imperative, the core motivation and founding values of humanitarianism, and
            underpins the other principles. In his 1979 <regular-italic>Commentary on the
                Fundamental Principles,</regular-italic> Pictet described humanity as requiring not
            only the preservation of life and physical integrity but also a respect for individual
            personality and dignity. Pictet emphasized that the principle must evolve with
            &#8216;circumstances&#8217;. The information age is one such circumstance. </normal>
        <normal>Dehumanization is no longer confined to explicit hate speech or fringe ideologies.
            It is increasingly embedded in everyday language, imagery and digital behaviours. It
            surfaces in manipulated images, inflammatory headlines and algorithmically amplified
            narratives that distort, erase or deny an individual&#8217;s humanity. In already
            fragile environments, the erosion of empathy is not just a side effect; it is often the
            intent. Dehumanization is not always overt. It can manifest subtly and systemically,
            including through digital profiling, unequal access to services or the commodification
            of personal data. At its core, dehumanization involves perceiving or treating someone as
            &#8216;less than human&#8217; &#8211; a denial of one or more elements of their
            humanity. While people never cease to be human, failing to recognize their humanity has
            real and often violent consequences. This includes reducing individuals to group
            identities (such as &#8216;migrant&#8217;, &#8216;refugee&#8217;), equating them with
            animals or vermin or disregarding their legitimate human interests and agency. When such
            rhetoric goes unchecked, it not only diminishes empathy and compassion but also
            increases public support for exclusion, retribution or even violence. It undermines
            helping behaviours, obstructs reconciliation and fuels policies and practices that may
            violate international law. </normal>
        <normal>Dehumanizing language and imagery directed at humanitarian action pose serious
            risks. They can be used to justify or encourage the obstruction of aid, lead to the
            targeting of humanitarian organizations, criminalize humanitarian assistance and render
            entire populations invisible or undeserving in the eyes of the public or
            decision-makers. These risks are particularly acute when such rhetoric originates from
            official sources or when humanitarian access is framed as politically motivated or a
            threat to national security. </normal>
        <normal>Yet even well-intentioned humanitarian actors can inadvertently replicate
            dehumanizing patterns if they are not actively mindful of the language they use or the
            power dynamics they reinforce. This is why principled humanitarianism must go beyond
            ethical commitment to uphold humanity: it must include deliberate efforts to detect and
            disrupt dehumanizing narratives, especially those normalized &#8220;in the undramatic
            episodes of the day-to-day&#8221;. The antidote to dehumanization is not simply more
            information &#8211; it is recognition. It is the act of restoring visibility and dignity
            to those denied it and reaffirming &#8211; through words, images and action &#8211; that
            no one is ever less than human. <bold>The humanitarian principles are not only capable
                of surviving today&#8217;s crisis of harmful information, they were designed to meet
            precisely this type of challenge. </bold></normal>
        <normal>The Movement has enormous capacity to act as a force amplifier for engagement
            through its staff and volunteers. National Societies seek to serve as trusted
            influencers who, by modelling the same positive behaviours online as they do offline in
            their communities, can help build healthier societies and shape norms of participation
            and response in the digital space.<fig href_fmt="images/p-ECU559-AB_fmt.jpg"
                href="file://images/p-ECU559-AB.tif"></fig>
        </normal>
        <h1-recommendations>Asks, aims and recommendations </h1-recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Asks </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Safeguard the fundamental and humanitarian principles &#8211; humanity,
            neutrality, impartiality and independence &#8211; across digital and offline spaces
            through collective action that protects access, safety and trust in humanitarian action,
            including the security of staff and populations in need. This includes respecting the
            legal and auxiliary roles of National Societies and ensuring that restrictive laws,
            sanctions or counter-terrorism measures do not undermine principled humanitarian action. </recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Aims </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Defend humanitarian principles from erosion by harmful information or
            politicized narratives and societal or political polarization. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Protect humanitarian access, safety and security by visibly upholding
            impartiality and neutrality and by advocating for humanitarian exemptions in legal and
            regulatory frameworks. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Reinforce community trust by co-creating narratives that reflect
            humanitarian principles, values and ethical practice, and by demonstrating the
            proportionality and objectivity of responses. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Advocate for responsible digital ecosystems &#8211; including algorithms
            and AI &#8211; that promote tolerance, strengthen social cohesion and reduce harmful
            information. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Support leadership and staff capacity to uphold the fundamental principles
            through training, codes of conduct, social media guidance and peer-to-peer exchanges. </recommendations>
        <recommendations>Strengthen humanitarian diplomacy and engagement with states, authorities,
            media and civil society to safeguard principled humanitarian action, counter harmful
            information and reinforce the credibility and operational effectiveness of the Movement. </recommendations>
        <h3>Recommendations </h3>
        <h4>States and policy-makers </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Safeguard humanitarian space in legislation, regulation and preparedness
            frameworks, ensuring the fundamental and humanitarian principles are respected in both
            digital and offline contexts. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Avoid instrumentalizing humanitarian actors in partisan or political
            agendas. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Publicly reaffirm and support the independence, impartiality and neutrality
            of humanitarian organizations. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Ensure humanitarian exemptions in sanctions, counter-terrorism and
            regulatory measures that might impede principled action. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Technology platforms </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Monitor and prevent harmful information targeting humanitarian action, with
            safeguards that respect fundamental rights. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Ensure transparency, tools and crisis protocols that enable principled
            humanitarian engagement online. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Act rapidly to address harassment and harmful information targeting
            humanitarian staff, volunteers and people in need. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Humanitarian actors </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Develop guidance for principled engagement in contested digital and online
            spaces, anticipating instrumentalized narratives and preparing clear communication lines
            in advance. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Reaffirm and communicate fundamental and humanitarian principles across
            platforms, avoiding partisan or political alignment. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Model adherence to the fundamental principles in words, behaviours and
            actions across all Movement components. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Equip staff and volunteers with digital security training, psychosocial
            support and information and media literacy to detect and respond to harmful narratives
            early. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Place renewed focus on addressing evolving challenges of intolerance across
            the Movement. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Foster reflection and learning on communication and humanitarian diplomacy,
            embedding humanitarian principles in responses to harmful information. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Involve community leaders and volunteers as validators and messengers,
            running sustained campaigns that highlight local impact and principled humanitarian
            action rather than relying only on reactive responses. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Communities and local leaders </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Act as trusted intermediaries reinforcing impartiality and bridging divides. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Identify polarized spaces and harmful information that threaten humanitarian
            access, trust and safety. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Co-create and amplify local narratives that reflect humanitarian values,
            ensuring humanitarian action remains responsive to community needs. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h1>The role of data in humanitarian decision-making </h1>
        <normal>The first questions asked when assessing a disaster or crisis are &#8216;how
            big/bad&#8217;, &#8216;where&#8217; and &#8216;to whom&#8217; the impacts will be felt.
            To answer these questions we need data. In recent years the volume of data produced to
            help answer these questions has mushroomed. As a result, the ability to build systematic
            methods for allocating resources, targeting assistance and anticipating crises has
            improved rapidly. Such methods enable humanitarian organizations to leverage evidence to
            guide our principles and rules with the aim of providing assistance where it is needed
            most. Building an evidence base for such principled decision-making requires
            transparency on what the data does &#8211; and does not &#8211; show; how it has been
            collected, produced or transformed; and how timely and reliable it is based on previous
            experience. </normal>
        <normal>The ability to collect data on disasters has improved in recent years, but recent
            defunding of many, often small and independent, data collection organizations threatens
            that ecosystem of evidence building. The evidence base upon which principled and
            effective humanitarian interventions are prioritized and implemented is, as a result,
            much poorer.<fig href_fmt="images/p-PAK3260-AB_fmt.jpg"
                href="file://images/p-PAK3260-AB.tif"></fig>
        </normal>
        <h1-recommendations>Asks, aims and recommendations </h1-recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Asks<bold> </bold></normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Sustain investment in disaster data systems at local, national and
            international levels, with particular support to National Societies and local actors to
            strengthen their capacities for data collection, analysis and sharing. </recommendations>
        <normal-2c>Aims </normal-2c>
        <recommendations>Enable more evidence-based humanitarian action and decision-making through
            improved data collection, analysis and use. </recommendations>
        <h3>Recommendations </h3>
        <h4>States and policy-makers </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Invest in comprehensive and reliable disaster data collection systems. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Commit to greater transparency and the use of evidence-based funding
            allocation processes. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Humanitarian actors </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Commit to generating and sharing the strongest possible evidence
            collectively, rather than advancing isolated evidence. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Work transparently to acknowledge data gaps and biases to ensure data and
            evidence are used appropriately. </bullet-list-2c>
        <h4>Communities and local leaders </h4>
        <bullet-list-2c>Insist on being involved in data collection and analysis, and assert your
            essential role in validating data and evidence generated by others. </bullet-list-2c>
        <bullet-list-2c>Work with humanitarian actors and donors to ensure community insights inform
            ongoing responses and interventions.</bullet-list-2c>
        <h1>Roadmap for resilience: Core pillars </h1>
        <normal>Building resilience against harmful information and safeguarding principled
            humanitarian action requires more than isolated interventions. It demands a coordinated,
            values-driven roadmap embedded across humanitarian diplomacy, community engagement and
            accountability, safer access initiatives, programme design, preparedness, risk
            management and communication strategies. The following eight pillars offer actionable
            steps across short-, medium- and longer-term horizons. </normal>
        <h2>Trust as a strategic asset </h2>
        <normal-tight>Trust is central to humanitarian action &#8211; supporting access, operational
            effectiveness, delivery and legitimacy. Harmful information seldom creates mistrust in
            humanitarian action on its own: it amplifies existing tensions, inconsistencies and
            perceived shortcomings. Trust is not static or binary. It exists on a spectrum shaped by
            cultural experience, power dynamics and exposure to harmful narratives. It evolves along
            a continuum: <bold>tell me  show me  prove it  keep proving it.</bold> At each stage
            of this continuum, trust can be weakened or strengthened, but never assumed; in
            humanitarian crises, it must be continually earned and safeguarded against the risks and
            corrosive effects of harmful information. </normal-tight>
        <normal>The messenger matters: volunteers, local staff and local leaders often serve as
            trust brokers. Supporting them to share accurate, timely and accessible information
            builds credibility from the ground up. Engagement and community information networks are
            central to resilience and to reduce the vacuum in which harmful information thrives.
            Leadership accountability and principled consistency across humanitarian organizations
            and operations are non-negotiable. People assess institutions not only by what they say,
            but by what they do and whether the two align. </normal>
        <normal>Two dimensions of trust are critical: </normal>
        <bullet-list><bold>Operational trust,</bold> grounded in presence and (human) proximity in
            interactions with affected communities, authorities, armed actors, media and peers. This
            trust must be personal and embodied: every staff member and volunteer must carry the
            organization&#8217;s humanitarian integrity in their behaviour, grounded in principles,
            standards and professionalism. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list><bold>Institutional trust</bold>, built through principled behaviour, ethical
            conduct, accountability and regulatory compliance so that stakeholders believe the
            organization&#8217;s stewardship, competence, effectiveness and values. </bullet-list>
        <h2>&#8216;Right-touch&#8217; compliance in a digital age </h2>
        <normal-expanded>Accountability in the information space is essential to sustaining trust
            and legitimacy in humanitarian action. Humanitarian organizations must apply the same
            standards of transparency, responsibility and protection to their communication as in
            their operations &#8211; verifying information, mitigating against harmful content and
            addressing unintended impacts. Feedback mechanisms should enable communities to question
            and influence how information about them is used. </normal-expanded>
        <normal>Humanitarian actors should promote norms and accountability across the information
            ecosystem &#8211; engaging with stakeholders from technology, media and states to uphold
            humanitarian principles and protect people in need from harm. </normal>
        <normal>While strong compliance systems support credibility and accountability, excessive
            bureaucracy and overly rigid procedures can erode trust, add unnecessary burden and
            weaken the human proximity that is central to humanitarian action. A
            &#8216;right-touch&#8217; (i.e., striking the right balance) approach balances
            safeguards with flexibility, ensuring compliance reinforces &#8211; not replaces &#8211;
            principled and ethical judgement and humanitarian integrity. </normal>
        <normal>States and other donors can support <bold>right-touch compliance</bold> by promoting
            due diligence that reinforces ethical judgement and humanitarian integrity, rather than
            imposing overly rigid procedures that slow responses or erode trust. Flexible frameworks
            ensure accountability while enabling principled, timely decision-making in complex
            operational and information environments. </normal>
        <h2>Informational and digital literacy and capacities </h2>
        <normal>Effective responses to harmful information require confidence and competence in
            navigating the information ecosystem and digital space, supported by strong internal
            capacities, technology access, strategic partnerships and shared standards. This shifts
            the focus from countering individual messages to understanding broader dynamics of how
            information is created, shared and trusted within communities, while emphasizing local
            media ecosystems, social trust and inclusive access to reliable information. </normal>
        <normal>Staff and volunteers should be equipped to navigate digital environments
            responsibly, recognize emerging threats and engage constructively. Collaborative
            partnerships with technology actors, civil society and media organizations help promote
            safe and principled digital practices and advocate for accountability where harm occurs.
            Community-based digital literacy should be viewed as a protection strategy &#8211;
            empowering people to assess, challenge and contextualize information. Coordination
            across the Movement and with external actors is essential to share insights, align
            standards and amplify principled voices, as no single actor can address this challenge
            alone. </normal>
        <normal>Co-creation with communities ensures they are active partners, not merely
            recipients, in shaping credible, context-appropriate responses. This approach considers
            five pillars: the <bold>message</bold> (content and framing), the <bold>medium</bold>
            (channels of transmission), the <bold>audience</bold>, the <bold>actors</bold> creating
            and circulating information, and the <bold>impact</bold> on people and systems. </normal>
        <normal>In a post-truth era, staying principled is both an ethical and operational
            necessity, and digital literacy and access are core enablers of trust and risk
            management. </normal>
        <normal-10>Information and digital literacy and access are now core enablers of trust and
            risk management. Limited literacy, especially at decision-making levels, undermines the
            ability to anticipate and respond effectively to harmful information. Without the
            skills, support and infrastructure to navigate today&#8217;s complex digital information
            environment, even the most principled strategies risk being reactive rather than
            anticipatory. </normal-10>
        <h2>Embed risk management in core systems </h2>
        <normal>Risk assessments should address not only physical and reputational risks but also
            trust-related vulnerabilities, including perception gaps, harmful narratives and
            community backlash. Humanitarian diplomacy must reaffirm the relevance of humanity,
            neutrality, impartiality and independence, especially in contested environments. </normal>
        <h2>Anticipation and integrated response strategies </h2>
        <normal>A proactive response begins with anticipation and foresight. Humanitarian actors
            must invest in tools and practices that help them understand and anticipate harmful
            information, not just react to it. This includes scenario planning, risk mapping and
            early warning systems to help identify potential sources, narratives and impacts on
            access, trust and safety. Understanding triggers and enablers &#8211; such as
            grievances, power dynamics and moments of societal stress &#8211; supports more targeted
            preparedness and response. Frameworks like the ABCDE approach can help map actors,
            messages, distribution mechanisms and effects, though they require analytical capacity
            and timely data access. </normal>
        <normal>Anticipatory strategies must be community led or guided, locally relevant and
            adaptive to evolving digital threats. </normal>
        <normal>Resilience demands more than reaction: it requires offensive, defensive and
            integrated proactive strategies connected in a cycle of protection and influence. </normal>
        <h2>Information diplomacy and norm setting </h2>
        <normal>Addressing harmful information requires more than technical fixes &#8211; it also
            demands dialogue, restraint and shared norms. Just as ceasefire agreements limit the use
            of physical weapons, <bold>harmful information diplomacy</bold> seeks to create
            voluntary guardrails around the instrumentalization of information. This complements
            existing humanitarian and peacebuilding efforts by preventing escalation, fostering
            trust and creating space for principled humanitarian action. </normal>
        <h2>Policy and governance for information resilience </h2>
        <normal>Policy gaps remain a barrier to systematic action. While tools exist, most
            organizations lack dedicated harmful information policies and safeguarding standards for
            digital engagement. Escalation frameworks for harmful information, protocols for
            volunteer and staff protection, and standardized understanding of harms and impacts are
            urgently needed. </normal>
        <h2>Research, evidence and partnerships </h2>
        <normal>Harmful information is borderless and adaptive; tackling it requires evidence,
            innovation and collaboration. At present, most humanitarian actors document incidents
            only anecdotally or as part of broader communication or access challenges. This leaves
            significant gaps in evidence: the human, social and operational impacts and harms of
            harmful information remain under-measured compared to physical damage to lives,
            infrastructure or livelihoods. Without this evidence base, policy responses risk being
            reactive, fragmented or misaligned with humanitarian principles. </normal>
        <normal>Greater investment is therefore needed in research, tools and partnerships that
            strengthen resilience at scale. Evidence turns anecdote into accountability. A robust
            understanding of the impacts of different forms of harmful information enables more
            effective advocacy with states, regulators and platforms, and helps ensure that
            humanitarian concerns are embedded in emerging governance frameworks. It also
            strengthens internal accountability by ensuring responses are data-driven, anticipatory
            and principled. </normal>
        <h1>Prerequisites and crosscutting enablers </h1>
        <normal>Building resilience to harmful information depends not only on trust, compliance,
            policy and partnerships, but also on a set of enabling conditions that determine whether
            recommendations translate into practice. Four enablers stand out: </normal>
        <h2>Crisis communication preparedness </h2>
        <normal-10>Effective responses to harmful information depend on preparedness before a crisis
            hits with established crisis communication structures with clear roles, escalation
            protocols and links to staff and volunteers. Regular environmental scanning and
            decision-making frameworks (when to engage publicly, prioritizing internal
            communication) ensure rapid, coordinated responses that balance transparency with risk
            management. </normal-10>
        <normal>In today&#8217;s complex information environment, communication is not merely a
            support function &#8211; it is a critical enabler of principled humanitarian action.
            Moving from reactive to strategic communication enables actors to shape the information
            environment through transparency, inclusion and dialogue &#8211; reinforcing trust and
            community resilience. Strategic and context-sensitive communication helps to safeguard
            humanitarian space, sustain access and build trust with communities. When grounded in
            sound analysis and principled practice, it can prevent the escalation of tensions and
            reduce harm through effective message framing, audience engagement and dialogue. The aim
            is to promote alternative narratives, enhance community resilience to harmful
            information and foster information and media literacy. This goes beyond just correcting
            falsehoods and aims to change behaviours. </normal>
        <normal-10>This requires an understanding of local drivers and triggers of harm, as well as
            investing in trusted, locally anchored engagement. Volunteers, including digital
            volunteers, can serve as early responders in the information ecosystem to detect and
            respond to emerging narratives, offering scalable, community-based interventions. This
            requires solid engagement, internal communication and support. Mapping influencers and
            narrative dynamics can build understanding of who shapes opinion in specific contexts
            and how that influence can be used constructively in support of humanitarian response. </normal-10>
        <normal><regular-italic>Timely, inclusive and principled communication is essential. </regular-italic>While
            information is not water or shelter, it often determines how &#8211; and whether &#8211;
            those needs are met and the basis on which people make decisions. </normal>
        <h2>Standardized tools and frameworks </h2>
        <normal>Fragmented responses increase vulnerability. Information Resilience or Information
            Integrity Toolkits<bold> </bold>(e.g., Movement Safer Access Framework (being updated),
            UNHCR Information Integrity Toolkit (2025), ICRC Framework (2025), IFRC Organizational
            Capacity Assessment and Certification) demonstrate how structured resources can provide
            a common approach to prevention, detection, escalation and response. Standardized,
            adaptable tools which could be socialized cross-sector and with digital rights groups,
            academia and the private sector to help humanitarians act faster and more consistently
            across contexts. </normal>
        <h2>Resourcing and professionalizing risk communication and community engagement </h2>
        <normal>Risk communication and community engagement (RCCE) is still too often treated as a
            &#8216;nice-to-have&#8217; rather than a core function. Underfunding, siloed
            coordination, limited localization and expertise gaps leave voids where harmful
            information thrives. To change this, RCCE must be embedded as a priority, with dedicated
            funding, trained multidisciplinary teams, proactive community partnerships and robust
            feedback loops. Ensure that humanitarian communication is not improvised but systematic,
            evidence-driven and locally anchored. </normal>
        <normal>Without these enablers, the six roadmap pillars risk being applied unevenly or only
            after harm is done. With them, humanitarian actors can move from fragmented, reactive
            responses to system-wide resilience: prepared, equipped and embedded in communities
            before, during and after crises. </normal>
        <h2>Harnessing influence for humanitarian resilience </h2>
        <normal>Resilience to harmful information depends on enabling trusted voices to carry
            principled narratives. Volunteers and frontline staff remain the strongest enablers,
            embedded in communities and building trust locally. Community leaders, youth networks,
            etc. amplify this trust and diaspora groups extend influence across borders. Independent
            media and journalists provide credibility through accurate reporting, and digital
            influencers and activists offer reach into fragmented online spaces, though with risks
            for neutrality. Above all, technology platforms act as &#8216;meta-influencers&#8217;,
            shaping which voices are amplified or suppressed. Advocacy for transparency and
            rights-respecting governance are vital. </normal>
        <normal>Ultimately, it is <bold>trust, not reach, that turns influence into resilience, </bold>safeguarding
            humanitarian space and ensuring that communities can act on accurate information. </normal>
        <normal>The IFRC&#8217;s <new-hyperlinks>Community Trust Index</new-hyperlinks> offers an
            evidence-based framework to measure, track and enhance trust between humanitarian
            organizations and the communities they serve. It assesses community perceptions across
            two dimensions: competence (technical skills, effectiveness, relevance) and values
            (integrity, transparency, participation) while also identifying enablers and barriers to
            trust in areas such as early warning systems, climate resilience, migration and public
            health. Other organizations and governments could adopt or adapt the index to generate
            structured, standardized data that complements real-time community feedback. This
            combination provides a reliable baseline and trend analysis to inform strategic
            decision-making. </normal>
        <normal-expanded>Looking ahead,<bold> </bold>the Community Trust Index could be further
            strengthened by integrating targeted focus on harmful information. Doing so would allow
            organizations to: track the spread and impact of rumours systematically, identify
            community segments most affected, and bridge qualitative feedback with quantitative
            insights. By evolving in this way, the index can help anticipate challenges and
            co-create tailored solutions with communities. Ultimately, the Community Trust Index is
            then more than a measurement tool &#8211; it is a call to action. By diagnosing trust
            gaps and empowering communities as partners, it equips organizations to rebuild and
            sustain trust well beyond crises. </normal-expanded>
        <h1>Systemic support needs </h1>
        <normal>Expertise and experiences highlight that addressing harmful information cannot rely
            on isolated projects or short-term fixes. Sustained resilience requires system-level
            investment, coordination and safeguards. Several gaps stand out: </normal>
        <bullet-list>Technical and analytical tools: Humanitarian actors need the ability to monitor
            both online and offline spaces, supported by data visualization, narrative and rumour
            trend mapping and predictive analytics to anticipate harmful narratives before they
            spread. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list>Monitoring and evaluation frameworks: Impact must be measured not only in
            outputs (e.g., messages delivered) but also in behavioural shifts, perception change and
            trust dynamics at community level. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list>Security protocols: Dedicated standards are needed for secure data handling and
            staff safety in contexts where armed groups or political actors monitor or exploit
            information systems. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list>Sustainable financing: Rumour-tracking and verification systems are
            resource-intensive. Without multi-year, flexible donor support, community capacity and
            infrastructure cannot be maintained or scaled. There is real potential for cross-sector
            collaboration to benefit from economies of scale. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list>Policy and coordination guidance: Clear roles, standards and escalation
            pathways are required within humanitarian coordination mechanisms to avoid fragmented or
            reactive responses. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list>Integration of local media: Community radio stations and local journalists
            should be actively engaged as frontline responders to harmful information, co-producing
            and distributing trusted, localized counter-messages. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list>Digital inclusion and platform accountability: Platforms must adapt their tools
            to humanitarian realities, providing low-bandwidth, multilingual and locally
            contextualized solutions while ensuring transparency and safeguards. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list>Ecosystem-wide literacy: Media and rumour literacy should be extended beyond
            technical staff to volunteers, health workers, teachers and community members, embedding
            resilience across whole populations. </bullet-list>
        <bullet-list>Anticipatory systems: Predictive modelling and pre-bunking strategies &#8211;
            delivered via SMS, posters or radio ahead of flashpoints such as elections or
            vaccination drives &#8211; can reduce the space for harmful rumours to take hold. </bullet-list>
        <normal>Together, these support needs point to a critical shift: from isolated interventions
            to systemic resilience, where humanitarian actors, governments, donors, platforms and
            communities co-invest in shared infrastructure for trustworthy information. </normal>
        <h1>Together, we can uphold and reclaim space for humanity </h1>
        <normal>Trust is not assured; it is built, reinforced and renewed. In the face of harmful
            information, it remains the most powerful safeguard for humanitarian space. By investing
            in trust, embedding right-touch compliance, addressing policy gaps and advancing
            evidence-based partnerships, the humanitarian sector can shift from reactive
            counter-narratives toward systemic resilience. </normal>
        <normal>Harmful information cannot be addressed piecemeal. Building resilience requires
            trust at the centre, compliance that enables rather than obstructs, integrated risk
            management, stronger policies, deeper evidence and partnerships &#8211; and above all,
            proactive strategies that connect defensive and offensive efforts. Silence and delay
            carry their own dangers; early, transparent, and trusted communication and engagement is
            the most powerful safeguard for humanitarian space. Governments need to act to preserve
            this humanitarian space. </normal>
        <normal>The humanitarian sector cannot afford to cede the information space. While the
            speed, scale and sophistication of harmful information poses significant challenges,
            disengagement is not a viable option. To maintain access, credibility and principled
            impact, humanitarian actors must engage deliberately grounded in the humanitarian
            principles, supported by collaboration and partnerships, and informed by a clear
            understanding of the social dynamics shaping today&#8217;s contested narratives. </normal>
        <normal>Reclaiming narrative space requires more than correcting harmful information. It
            calls for a reframing of communication as connection, rooted in listening, empathy,
            proximity, humility and consistency. It also requires organizations to understand how
            harmful information spreads and why people believe or accept it, addressing not just the
            content of falsehoods but the emotions, fears and identities that give them power. </normal>
        <normal>In times of crisis, harmful information thrives by reducing complex realities into
            simplistic explanations and easily identifiable enemies. Principled humanitarian action
            must not only speak truth, it must also understand fear, identity and belonging. In this
            fragmented, emotionally charged landscape, reclaiming narrative space is not about
            controlling the story. It is about restoring trust, rebuilding connection and
            reasserting the relevance of humanitarian principles and action in the eyes of affected
            communities and the broader public. Governments have an important role in this regard to
            reinforce the importance of principled humanitarian action and preserving the space for
            humanitarian organizations to operate. </normal>
        <normal>The Movement&#8217;s Resolution on Tolerance offers a valuable foundation to
            reinvigorate efforts against harmful information &#8211; reminding us that respect,
            diversity and non-discrimination are not abstract ideals but practical tools to reduce
            polarization, counter dehumanizing narratives and preserve humanitarian space. Tolerance
            online also has its limits: &#8220;what is often framed as a fight over <regular-italic>
            speech</regular-italic> is actually a fight over <regular-italic>reach&#8221; </regular-italic>(DiResta)
            &#8211; the algorithmic amplification that determines which voices are elevated,
            repeated and made unavoidable. The humanitarian sector must advocate for changes that
            reduce the reach of hate speech and malicious content that imperil humanitarian action
            and endanger staff, volunteers and crisis-affected populations. </normal>
        <normal>The scale of the challenge may feel overwhelming, but it need not paralyse us. By
            acting collectively &#8211; rooted in principles, grounded in trust and united across
            communities, states, platforms and humanitarian organizations &#8211; the sector can
            move forward with courage and clarity. </normal>
        <normal>The intersection of resilience, principled communication and institutional
            credibility is now a critical arena for action. Humanitarian actors must shift from a
            defensive posture to proactive, adaptive and systematic approaches that prepare for and
            mitigate the impact of harmful information, particularly where it threatens access,
            undermines trust or endangers lives. Delivering this requires a cross-functional
            approach in collaboration with communities. </normal>
        <normal>
            <bold>The right to information is contested, but in humanitarian crises, the need to
                know elevates information to a core element of response. </bold>
        </normal>
        <normal>
            <bold>Together, we can uphold and reclaim space for humanity.</bold>
        </normal>
    </Story>
    <fig href_fmt="images/p-CMR481-AB.jpg" href="file://images/p-CMR481-AB.tif"></fig>
</Story>